Euan Thomas McGonigle®

School of Mathematics Fry Building University of Bristol Bristol, BS8 1UG, UK

Research Interests

My research interests primarily lie in nonstationary time series, change point detection and wavelet methods in statistics. My current research has a strong emphasis on the development of new statistical models and methodology for analysing time series that display time-varying statistical properties, with particular interest in applications to environmental science and finance.

Professional Experience

Research Associate

Bristol, UK

School of Mathematics, University of Bristol

Aug. 2020 - present

Email: euan.mcgonigle@bristol.ac.uk

Website: euanmcgonigle.github.io

Research areas: change point analysis, nonstationary time series

Research Intern

Lancaster, UK

STOR-i Centre for Doctoral Training, Lancaster University

Jul. 2015 - Sep. 2015

Research topic: Used Bayesian change point analysis to model linguistic style of the author Fanny Burney.

EDUCATION

Lancaster University

Lancaster, UK

PhD in Statistics and Operational Research

Oct. 2017 - Jul. 2020

Supervisors: Rebecca Killick and Matthew Nunes

Thesis title: Wavelet Methods for Locally Stationary Time Series

Lancaster University

Lancaster, UK

MRes in Statistics and Operational Research; Distinction

Oct. 2016 - Sep. 2017

Dissertation title: Novel Wavelet Models for Nonstationary Time Series

University of Glasgow

Glasgow, UK

Msci in Mathematics; First class honours

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2016

PUBLICATIONS

• Refereed Journal Articles

- McGonigle, E. T. and Cho, H. (2022+) Robust multiscale estimation of time-average variance for time series segmentation. *Computational Statistics and Data Analysis* (to appear). [Open Access link] [Link to code on Github].
- o McGonigle, E. T., Killick, R., and Nunes, M. A. (2022) Modelling time-varying first and second-order structure of time series via wavelets and differencing. *Electronic Journal of Statistics*, 16 (2):4398-4448. [Open Access link] [Link to code on Github].
- McGonigle, E. T., Killick, R., and Nunes, M. A. (2022) Trend locally stationary wavelet processes. Journal of Time Series Analysis, 43(6):895?917. [Open Access link] [Link to code on Github].
- McGonigle, E. T., Killick, R., and Nunes, M. A. (2021) Detecting change in mean in the presence of time-varying autocovariance. *Stat* 10 (1), e351. [Open Access link].

• Preprints

o McGonigle, E. T. and Peng, H. (2021) Subspace Change-Point Detection via Low-Rank Matrix Factorisation. *ArXiv preprint arXiv:2110.04044*. [arXiv link].

Invited

• Change point detection for complex time series data

EcoSta 2021 (virtual), HKUST, Hong Kong

Jun. 2021

Modelling nonstationary time series with wavelets and differencing

University of Bristol Statistics Seminar, UK

Nov. 2020

Modelling nonstationary time series with wavelets

Numerical Algorithms Group, Oxford, UK

Oct. 2019

o Detecting changes in mean in the presence of autocovariance

2019 Joint Statistical Meetings, Denver, Colorado, USA

Jul. 2019

Contributed

Nonparametric change point analysis of multivariate time series

Royal Statistical Society International Conference 2022, Aberdeen, UK

September 2022

 Modelling time-varying first and second-order structure of time series via wavelets and differencing

Lancaster University Workshop on Time Series and Spatial Statistics, UK

May 2020

Detecting changes in mean in the presence of autocovariance

STOR-i PhD forum, Lancaster, UK

May 2019

Locally stationary wavelet processes with trend

STOR-i PhD forum, Lancaster, UK

Jun. 2018

TEACHING & SUPERVISION

Teaching

- o **Tutor**, University of Bristol, Jan. 2021 present
 - * Tutor for 1st year Probability
 - * Ran online drop-in sessions for 3rd year Multivariate Analysis
- Lecturer, Introduction to R Programming, Lancaster University, Jul. 2018 Jul. 2019 Prepared and delivered an R training course for the STOR-i research interns.
- o Graduate Teaching Assistant, Lancaster University, 2017 2020 Delivered workshops and tutorials in a range of modules:
 - * MATH103 Probability I
 - * MATH104 Statistics
 - * MATH105 Linear Algebra I
 - * MATH215 Complex Analysis
 - * MATH225 Abstract Algebra
 - * MATH230 Probability II
 - * MATH235 Statistics II
 - * MATH334 Time Series Analysis
 - * STOR605 Inference and Modelling
- Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, University of Glasgow, Jan. May 2016 Undergraduate teaching assistant for Mathematics 2D Topics in Linear Algebra and Calculus.

• Supervision

o STOR-i 2018 Summer Internship, Supervisor, Lancaster University, Jul. - Sep. 2018 My responsibility was to design a research project and supervise an undergraduate research intern.

Honours & Awards

• Research Conference Travel Fund, Lancaster University

Feb. 2020

• Dougall Prize for Distinction in Honours Mathematics, University of Glasgow

Jun. 2016

OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Refereeing: Journal of the American Statistical Association, Environmental and Ecological Statistics, Journal of the Korean Statistical Society, Journal of Multivariate Analysis, Journal of Statistical Software, Statistics and Computing.
- Consultancy: Have participated in the Statistics Clinic, a free statistical consulting service for researchers at University of Bristol since 2021.
- Memberships: Fellow of the Royal Statistical Society.

SERVICE

- Student representative for Masters students, Lancaster University, 2016 2017.
- STOR-i Centre for Doctoral Training website organiser, 2017 2020.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: R (advanced), MATLAB (intermediate), C (intermediate).
- Programming Skills: R Package development, interfacing R with C.